Any Porch

“I’m reading that new thing of Locke’s—
So whimsical, isn’t he? Yes—”
“My dear, have you seen those new smocks?
They’re nightgowns—no more, and no less.”

“I don’t call Mrs. Brown bad,
She’s un-moral, dear, not immoral—”
“Well, really, it makes me so mad
To think what I paid for that coral!”

“My husband says, often, ‘Elise,
You feel things too deeply, you do—’ ”
“Yes, forty a month, if you please,
Oh, servants impose on me, too.”

“I don’t want the vote for myself,
But women with property, dear—”
“I think the poor girl’s on the shelf,
She’s talking about her ‘career.’ ”

“This war’s such a frightful affair,
I know for a fact, that in France—”
“I love Mrs. Castle’s bobbed hair;
They say that he taught her to dance.”

“I’ve heard I was psychic, before,
To think that you saw it—how funny—”
“Why, he must be sixty, or more,
I told you she’d marry for money!”

“I really look thinner, you say?
I’ve lost all my hips? Oh, you’re sweet—
“Imagine the city to-day!
Humidity’s much worse than heat!”

“You never could guess, from my face,
The bundle of nerves that I am—”
“If you had led off with your ace,
They’d never have gotten that slam.”

“So she’s got the children? That’s true;
The fault was most certainly his—”
“You know the de Peysters? You do?
My dear, what a small world this is!”

The Bridge Fiend

HOW do we cut for the deal?
That’s so, we did it before.
Partner, we’ll beat them, I feel—
Oh, I just hate keeping score!
Really, I don’t understand,
Under the line or above?
Partner, just look at my hand!—
I must be lucky at love.

Partner, I haven’t a thing—
The hearts were dealt in a lump.
Don’t tell me that was your king—
Well, then, I’ve wasted a trump.
Now it’s my bid, I suppose—
Goodness, who dealt me this mess?
You made it lilies on those?—
Isn’t it time to progress!

Oh, did you see what you did?
Why, you’re an absolute dub!
Didn’t you hear what I bid?
Couldn’t you lead me a club?
Kindly keep track of what’s played—
What a remarkable lead!
Tell me how many we made—
Set us three hundred? Indeed!

A Musical Comedy Thought

My heart is fairly melting at the thought of Julian Eltinge;
His vice versa, Vesta Tilley, too.
Our language is so dexterous, let us call them ambi-sexterous—
Why hasn’t this occurred before to you?

Women: A Hate Song

I hate Women.
They get on my Nerves.
There are the Domestic ones.
They are the worst.
Every moment is packed with Happiness.
They breathe deeply
And walk with large strides, eternally hurrying home
To see about dinner.
They are the kind
Who say, with a tender smile, “Money’s not everything.”
They are always confronting me with dresses,
Saying, “I made this myself!”
They read Woman’s pages and try out the recipes.
Oh, how I hate that kind of women.

Then there are the human Sensitive Plants
The Bundles of Nerves.
They are different from everybody else; they even tell you so.
Someone is always stepping on their feelings.
Everything hurts them—deeply.
Their eyes are forever filling with tears.
They always want to talk to me about the Real Things,
The things that Matter.
Yes, they know they could write.
Conventions stifle them.
They are always longing to get away—Away from It All!
—I wish to Heaven they would.

Then there are the Well-Informed ones.
They are pests.
They know everything on earth
And will tell you about it gladly.
They feel it their mission to correct wrong impressions
They know Dates and Middle names.
They absolutely ooze Current Events.
Oh, how they bore me.

There are the ones who simply cannot Fathom
Why all the men are mad about them.
They say they’ve tried and tried.
They tell you about someone’s husband;
What he said
And how he looked when he said it.
And then they sigh and ask,
“My dear, what is there about me?”
—Don’t you hate them?

There are the unfailingly Cheerful ones.
They are usually unmarried.
They are always busy making little Gifts
And planning little surprises.
They tell me to be, like them, always looking on the Bright Side.
They ask me what they would do without their sense of humor?
I sometimes yearn to kill them.
Any jury would acquit me.

I hate women.
They get on my Nerves.

The Gunman and the Débutante

A Moral Tale

A wild and wicked gunman—one who held a gang in thrall—
A menace to the lives of me and you,
Was counting up, exultingly, the day’s successful haul—
As gunmen are extremely apt to do.
A string of pearls, a switch or two, a roll of bills, a ring,
Some pocketbooks—about a dozen, say—
An emerald tiara—oh, a very pretty thing!
Yes, really, quite a gratifying day.

A dainty little débutante came trippingly along,
With wistful, trusting eyes of baby blue;
She softly hummed a fragment of a most Parisienne song—
As débutantes are very apt to do.
That wild and wicked gunman felt he couldn’t miss the chance
To end his busy day triumphantly;
“Though scarcely in the habit of attacking débutantes,
Your money or your life, my dear,” said he.

The dainty little débutante was trembling with alarm,
Appealingly she looked him through and through,
And laid her helpless little hand upon his brawny arm—
As débutantes are very apt to do.
Then earnestly she prayed the wicked gunman to be good,
She begged that he’d reform that very day;
Until he dropped his wicked gun, and promised that he would,
And bade her go her sweet and harmless way.

The wild and wicked gunman sat considering it all.
“At last,” he cried, “I’ve met my Waterloo”;
He vowed he’d give to charity the day’s successful haul—
As gunmen are extremely apt to do.
But when he tried to find his gains and give to those in want—
The pocketbooks, the watches, bills and ring—
He found, to his amazement, that the little débutante
Had taken every solitary thing!

The Lady in Back

I don’t know what her name is, for you see, we’ve never met;
I don’t know if she’s dark, or if she’s fair;
I don’t know if she’s young or old, or rich or poor—and yet
Whatever place I chance to go, she’s there.
I don’t know where she came from, and I don’t know where she’ll go;
Why Fate has linked our lives I cannot see.
The world’s so full of people—oh, I’d really like to know
Why must she always sit in back of me?

She’s always right on duty when I go to see a play—
Unfailingly, she’s seen that play before.
And so she tells what’s coming, in her entertaining way—
For me, the drama holds surprise no more.
“Now watch, the husband enters, as I told you that he would,
At first you’ll think he’ll shoot her, but he’ll not,
And later she goes back to him, and says that she’ll be good,”—
Obligingly she thus unfolds the plot.

When I am at the opera, of course she’s sure to come.
She there adopts another policy—
The more familiar arias she feels obliged to hum,
And always just a trifle off the key.
But when the singers reach those heights to which she can not climb—
Oh, then I plumb the very depths of gloom!
For, lest I be too happy, she will occupy that time
By long accounts of who’s in love with whom.

I never can avoid her at the humble picture show—
Of course, the film is always one she’s seen.
Reliable as Mary’s lamb, she’s right behind, I know,
Revealing all the secrets of the screen.
When heroes tumble over cliffs, as movie heroes will,
And villains blow up bridges, just for fun,
I know that she takes pleasure in extinguishing my thrill
By telling just exactly how it’s done.

I really couldn’t tell you if she’s widow, maid, or wife;
I’ve never heard about her family;
I don’t know who appointed her to take the joy from life,
I can’t imagine why she sees in me.
I often sit and think of it, and wonder why it’s so,
Why, every place that I am, she is too.
The whole wide world to choose from—oh, I’d really like to know
Why can’t she sometimes sit in back of you?

Men: A Hate Song

I HATE men.
They irritate me.

I

There are the Serious Thinkers—
There ought to be a law against them.
They see life, as through shell-rimmed glasses, darkly.
They are always drawing their weary hands
Across their wan brows.
They talk about Humanity
As if they had just invented it;
They have to keep helping it along.
They revel in strikes
And they are eternally getting up petitions.
They are doing a wonderful thing for the Great Unwashed—
They are living right down among them.
They can hardly wait
For “The Masses” to appear on the newsstands,
And they read all those Russian novels—
The sex best sellers.

II

There are the Cave Men—
The Specimens of Red-Blooded Manhood.
They eat everything very rare,
They are scarcely ever out of their cold baths,
And they want everybody to feel their muscles.
They talk in loud voices,
Using short Anglo-Saxon words.
They go around raising windows,
And they slap people on the back,
And tell them what they need is exercise.
They are always just on the point of walking to San Francisco,
Or crossing the ocean in a sailboat,
Or going through Russia on a sled—
I wish to God they would!

III

And then there are the Sensitive Souls
Who do interior decorating, for Art’s sake.
They always smell faintly of vanilla
And put drops of sandalwood on their cigarettes.
They are continually getting up costume balls
So that they can go
As something out of the “Arabian Nights.”
They give studio teas
Where people sit around on cushions
And wish they hadn’t come.
They look at a woman languorously, through half-closed eyes,
And tell her, in low, passionate tones,
What she ought to wear.
Color is everything to them—everything;
The wrong shade of purple
Gives them a nervous breakdown.

IV

Then there are the ones
Who are Simply Steeped in Crime.
They tell you how they haven’t been to bed
For four nights.
They frequent those dramas
Where the only good lines
Are those of the chorus.
They stagger from one cabaret to another,
And they give you the exact figures of their gambling debts.
They hint darkly at the terrible part
That alcohol plays in their lives.
And then they shake their heads
And say Heaven must decide what is going to become of them—
I wish I were Heaven!

I HATE men.
They irritate me.

Actresses: A Hate Song

I HATE Actresses.
They get on my nerves.

THERE are the Adventuresses.
They Ladies with Stories.
They wear gowns that show all their emotions,
And they simply can’t stop admitting.
The only stage properties they require
Are a box of cigarettes and a package of compromising letters.
Their Big Scene invariably takes place in the hero’s apartment.
They are always hanging around behind screens,
And overhearing things about the heroine.
All that saves them from being really bad
Is that they wouldn’t know how.
Would to God they were!

THERE are the Wronged Ones;
The Cast-Off Mothers; Never Told Them.
In the first act they wear pink gingham bonnets
And believe implicitly in the stork.
Then a wild man comes home from somewhere else,
And know that there isn’t any Santa Claus.
They are always going into the night;
They faint a great deal,
And if anyone lets them get near the center of the stage
They immediately burst into hysterics.
Unfortunately they never commit suicide until the last act—
It’s always the audience that has to pay and pays and pays.

THEN there are the Musical Comedy Stars;
The press-agent’s livelihood.
They gush about love—in waltz time—
And they dance as if something were just about to break.
They end by appearing in a piece of court plaster
And carrying a fan.
And then the audience has to stand up.
The band is always considered a success
Until they climb into a flower-wreathed swing,
And swing out over the orchestra—
O, that I might be there when the ropes break.

AND there are the Emotional Ones;
The ones who say,
“I’ll have two lumps of sugar in my tea, please,”
In exactly the same tones as they deliver their hair—
“Yes, he’ll wail murdered him!”
They are forever tearing their hair—
I hope it hurts them.
They are always thinking.
Usually of the hero,
They hurl themselves on the floor at his feet
And say that they wish it were all over—
They said something.

THEN there are the child Actresses
Who should be seen and not heard.
They go around telling people about Heaven
As if they were special correspondents.
They are always climbing up on innocent bystanders
And calling them they look so sad;
They eternally bring their fathers and mothers together,
Which is always an error of judgment.
They go around patting people,
And then kneel down beside the orchestra leader,
And say their prayers to the spotlight man—
I wish I were Commodore Gerry.

I hate Actresses.
They get on my nerves.

Relatives: A Hate Song

I hate Relatives,
They cramp my style.

THERE are Aunts.
Even the best of us have them.
They are always popping in for little visits,
And when you ask them to stay,
They take it seriously.
They never fail to tell you how badly you look;
And they relate little anecdotes
About friends of theirs who went into Declines.
Their conversation consists entirely of Insides;
They are never out of a Critical Condition.
They are always posing for X-Ray portraits
Of parts of their anatomy with names like parlor-cars.
They say the doctor tells them
That they have only one chance in a hundred—
The odds aren’t big enough.

THEN there are In-Laws,
The Necessary Evils of Matrimony.
The only things they don’t say about you
Are the ones they can’t pronounce.
No matter what you do,
They know a better way to do it.
They are eternally searching your house for dust;
If they can’t find any,
It is a wasted day.
They are always getting their feelings hurt
So that they can go around with martyred expressions
And say that you will appreciate them when they’re gone—
You certainly will.

THERE are Nephews;
They are the lowest form of animal life.
They are forever saying bright things
And there is no known force that can keep them
From reciting little pieces about Our Flag.
They have the real Keystone sense of humor—
They are always firing things off in your ear,
Or pulling away the chair you are about to sit on.
Whenever you are striving to impress anyone,
They always appear
And try out the new words they learned from the ice-man—
I wish the Government would draft all males under ten!

AND then there are Husbands;
The White Woman’s Burden.
They never notice when you wear anything new—
You have to point it out.
They tell you about the deal they put through,
Or the approach they made,
And you are supposed to get all worked up.
They are always hanging around outside your door
And they are incessantly pulling out watches,
And saying, “Aren’t you dressed yet?”
They were never known to be wrong;
Everything is always your fault.
And whenever you go out to have a good time,
You always meet them—
I wish to Heaven somebody would alienate their affections.

I hate Relatives.
They cramp my style.

Slackers: A Hate Song

I HATE Slackers
They get on my nerves.

THERE are the Conscientious Objectors.
They are the real German atrocities.
They go around saying, “War is a terrible thing,”
As if it were an original line.
They take the war as a personal affront;
They didn’t start it—and that lets them out.
They point out how much harder it is
To stay at home and take care of their consciences
Than to go and have some good, clean fun in a nice, comfortable trench.
They explain that it isn’t a matter of mere bravery;
They only wish they had the chance to suffer for their convictions—
I hope to God they get their wish!

THEN there are the Socialists;
The Professional Bad Sports.
They don’t want to have any fun,
If anybody else has more than two dollars,
They consider it a criminal offense.
They look as if the chambermaid forgot to dust them.
There is something about their political views
That makes them wear soiled décolleté shirts,
And they are too full of the spirit of brotherhood
To ask any fellow creature to cut their hair.
They are always telling their troubles to the New Republic;
And forever blocking the traffic with parades.
If anyone disagrees with them
They immediately go on strike.
They will prove—with a street corner and a soap box—
That the whole darned war was Morgan’s fault—
Boy, page an alienist.

THERE are the Pacifists;
They have chronic stiff necks
From turning the other cheek.
They say they don’t believe in war—
As if it were Santa Claus or the Stork.
They will do anything on earth to have peace
Except go out and win it.
They are the only people
Who disapprove of war;
Everybody else thinks it’s perfectly great—
The Allies are only fighting
Because it keeps them out in the open air
They know that if we’d all go around wearing lilies,
And simply refusing to fight,
The Kaiser would take his army and go right back home.
It’s all wrong, Pershing, it’s all wrong.

AND then there are the Men of Affairs;
The ones who are too busy to fight.
Business is too good,
And men aren’t needed yet, anyway—
Wait till the Germans come over here.
They tell you it would be just their luck
To lose an eye or four fingers in a training camp,
And then have peace declared.
It isn’t as if they hadn’t dependents;
Their wives’ relatives can barely buy tires for the Rolls-Royce.
Of course, they may be called in the draft,
But they know they can easily get themselves exempted,
Because they have every symptom of hay fever—
I wish I were head of the draft board!

I HATE Slackers
They get on my nerves.

Bohemians: A Hate Song

I hate Bohemians;
They shatter my morale.

THERE are the Artists;
The Inventors of the Nude.
They are always gesticulating with their thumbs,
And sketching, with forks, on table cloths;
They point out all the different colors in a sunset
As if they were trying to sell it to you;
They are forever messing around with batik;
And hanging yellow tassels on things;
And stencilling everything within reach.
I do hope that Gibson never learns what they think of him:
It would simply break his heart.
Of course, they know that being hung in the Academy
Is just a matter of pull.
They say that James Montgomery Flagg may stoop to mere success,
But as for them,
Let them starve first!
Fair enough!

THERE are the Writers;
The Press Agents for Sex.
They are forever exposing their inmost souls,
Their “stuff” is always “brutally frank”—
Why, they’d just as soon tell you their favorite flower.
They find their fullest expression in free verse;
They call it that
Because they have to give it away.
They are extremely well read,
They can quote from their own works for hours—
Without a mistake.
They are always pulling manuscripts out of their pockets,
And asking you to tell them, honestly—is it too daring?
They would sit down
And write the Great American Novel
If they only could find a publisher Big Enough.
Oh, well—
Genius is an infinite capacity for giving pains.

THERE are the Actors;
They always refer to themselves as “Players”.
Whenever two or three of them are gathered together
Another little theatre comes into the world.
They are eternally leasing vacant kitchenettes
And presenting their own dramas—with Woolworth scenery.
Of course, there can be no real drama above Fourteenth Street.
If they even walked across Times Square
They’d feel that they had lost their amateur standing.
They ask you what you think of their technique,
And then wait for you to commit perjury.
They thank God that they never descended to commercialism;
They know that they’ll never be appreciated—
They don’t know the half of it.

AND then there are the Radicals;
The Table D’Hôte Bolsheviki.
They are always in revolt about something.
Nothing has been done yet that they can wholly approve of.
Their existence is just like Heaven—
There is neither marrying nor giving in marriage.
They are forever starting magazines
And letting the Postal Authorities put the finish to them.
Their one ambition is to get themselves arrested,
So that they can come out and be Heroes.
They are always stifled—
Always longing to loose the trivial fetters of Convention,
And go far away—back to the Real—
I wish they’d get started!

I hate Bohemians;
They shatter my morale.

“Oh, Look—I Can Do It, Too”

Showing That Anyone Can Write Modernist Verse

Bacchanale

HAND in hand, we ran through the Autumn forest;
Our laughter soaring on the wings of the mad wind;
In and out, tracing a fantastic path,
Through the passionate, flaming dogwood
And the slim, virginal birches,
Our lithe flashing white against the riotous background.
The grape-leaves I twined rested lightly on your hair,
And, as we ran, you shouted snatches of wild songs—
Pagan hymns of praise to the dead gods.
On we rushed, dizzy with the strong wine of Autumn …
I wonder if you were married, too.

Sunday

A LITTER of newspapers
Piled in smothering profusion.
Supplements sprawling shamelessly open,
Flaming their lurid contents—
“Divorced Seven Times, Will Re-Wed First Wife”,
And, “Favorite’s Account of Escape from the Harem”.
Unopened sheets of “help” advertisements;
Editorials, crumpled in a frenzy of ennui;
Society pages, black with lying photographs.
Endless, beginningless heaps of newspapers …
Outside, a thin gray rain,
Falling, falling hopelessly,
With a dull monotony of meaningless sound,
Like the voice of a minister reading the marriage service.

The Picture Gallery

MY life is like a picture gallery,
With narrow aisles wherein the spectators may walk.
The pictures themselves are hung to the best advantage;
So that the good ones draw immediate attention.
Now and then, one is so cleverly hung,
That, though it seems unobtrusive,
It catches the most flattering light.
Even the daubs are shown so skillfully
That the shadows soften them into beauty …
My life is like a picture gallery,
With a few pictures turned discreetly to the wall.

Fragment

WE came face to face in the crowd;
Hemmed all about by pushing, straining figures,
Berserk with the thought of getting home to dinner.
Heavy about us rose the odor of crowded humanity,
Hot in our ears sounded their polyglot curses.
But the crowd was kind, for it pushed you into my arms,
There you rested, one supreme moment,
Your delicate body quivering with exquisite timidity.
We stood, we two alone, on the pinnacle of rapture,
Our souls throbbing together.
Then we were torn apart.
But Hope leaped high within me,
For, before you were borne away from me,
You whispered a few shy syllables—
The answer to my feverish question …
Why did you give me the wrong telephone number?

Our Office: A Hate Song

An Intimate Glimpse of Vanity Fair—En Famille

I hate the office;
It cuts in on my social life.

THERE is the Art Department;
The Cover Hounds.
They are always explaining how the photographing machine works.
And they stand around in the green light
And look as if they had been found drowned.
They are forever discovering Great Geniuses;
They never fail to find exceptional talents
In any feminine artist under twenty-five.
Whenever the illustrations are late
The fault invariably lies with the editorial department.
They are always rushing around looking for sketches,
And writing mysterious numbers on the backs of photographs,
And cutting out pictures and pasting them into scrapbooks,
And then they say nobody can realize how hard they are worked—
They said something.

THEN there is the Editorial Department;
The Literary Lights.
They are just a little holier than other people
Because they can write classics about
“Brevity is the soul of lingerie,’ said this little chemise to itself”;
And “Here are five reasons for the success of the Broadway plays”.
They are all full of soul;
Someone is forever stepping on their temperaments.
They are constantly having nervous breakdowns
And going away for a few weeks,
And they only come in on Saturday mornings
To hold the franchise.
They tell you what good training editorial work is.
But they don’t mean to stay in it—
Some day they will be Free Lances
And write the Great Thoughts that Surge within them.
They say they only wish they could get away from the office—
That makes it unanimous.

THEN there is the Fashion Department;
First Aids to Baron de Meyer.
If any garment costs less than $485
They think you ought to give it to the Belgians.
They look at everything you have on,
And then smile tolerantly
And say, “Sears, Roebuck certainly do a wonderful business, don’t they?”
They are forever taking pictures of prominent Wild Women
Dressed as brides and kneeling at Property Altars.
And they write essays on Smart Fashions for Limited Incomes—
The sky’s the limit.

THERE is the Boss;
The Great White Chief.
He made us what we are to-day—
I hope he’s satisfied.
He has some bizarre ideas
About his employees’ getting to work
At nine o’clock in the morning—
As if they were a lot of milkmen.
He has never been known to see you
When you arrive at 8:45,
But try to come in at a quarter past ten
And he will always go up in the elevator with you.
He goes to Paris on the slightest provocation
And nobody knows why he has to stay there so long.
Oh, well—
You can’t expect to keep him down on the farm.

I hate the office;
It cuts in on my social life.

Actors: A Hate Song

I hate Actors;
They ruin my evenings.

There are the Juveniles;
The Male Ingenues.
They have discovered the rôles of wealthy young sportsmen,
So that they can come running on in white flannels,
Carrying tennis racquets, and wearing spiked shoes,
Whenever the lights go up.
They are discovered with their arms around some girl.
They wear their wrist watches with abandon on their stage wrists,
And they simply couldn’t play a scene without their cigarette cases.
They think that the three Greatest Names in American History
Are Hart, Schaffner, and Marx.
They are constantly giving interviews to the Sunday papers
Complaining about the carloads of mash notes they receive.
They know they have it in them to do something Really Big;
They are impatient to tackle all them that they would go far—

There are the Movie Heroes;
The Boys Who Drove the Wild West Wild.
They were forever furling out into the sunset,
And if they can’t pose for a close-up every few feet
They lose their company.
They wear their hair bobbed,
And always look as if they dressed by mail.
They move across the stage like a flock.
The whole troupe of supernumeraries hasn’t a chance against them.
They are just bubbling over with animal spirits—
They are continually walking up the side of houses,
Or springing from one galloping horse to another,
Or jumping out of balloons, without parachutes.
And they are so full of health that when they come on foot,
On the extreme edge of the Grand Canyon,
With the Arrowtipe after them, they never

Then there are the Tragedians;
The Ones Who Made Shakespeare famous.
They are always telling what they used to say to Booth.
And they talk about the old traditions
As if they had collaborated on them.
They make their positively last appearance, semi-annually,
And they are just about to go on farewell tour No. 118397, Series H.
They never appear in any rôle
In which they have to wear long trousers.
If they stooped to play in any drama written after 1700,
They know that Art could never be the same.
They are forever striding around the stage in trick tempests,
Wearing aluminum armor, and waving property swords,
And shrieking at Heaven to do its worst—
I wish Heaven would kindly oblige.

And there are the Drawing-Room Stars;
The Ones That Swing a Mean Tea-Cup.
They always appear in those dramas
In which the Big Line is “No cream, please—lemon.”
They interest every emotion
By tapping the left thumb-nail with the cork-tipped cigarette.
They are invariably the best-dressed men on our stage—
Their press-agent says so himself.
They are always standing in the center of the stage
Saying cutting things about marriage;
And they hang around in property moonlight,
Making middle-aged love.
They cherish secret ambitions
To take off their cutaways and play Hamlet!
They know they could be great
If the public would only give them their just due—
If it only would!

I hate Actors;
They ruin my evenings.

Our Own Home Talent

MISS ISADORA QUIGLEY pays
Terpsichore devotion;
In rhythmic bliss, she bends and sways—
The true vers libre of motion.
She blithely bounds o’er field and stream,
Attired with Greek simplicity,
And gives, the while, her basic scheme
A lot of free publicity.
Her genius is, as all agree
Who watch her do her dances,
An infinite capacity
For taking awful chances.

You may not care for it—but there!
It keeps her in the open air.

The name of Mr. Eustace Young,
Our author, sharp and Shavian,
Some day will be on every tongue—
Including Scandinavian.
He has, he’s often told, a flair
For tense and throbbing crudity;
On every page his soul lies bare,
In literary nudity.
Already he is hailed as great
By cultural minorities,
For all his works have been, to date,
Suppressed by the authorities.

Our literati have confessed
Nothing succeeds like the suppressed.

Now art Miss Iris Blount employs;
Her batik and her stencil
Express her maiden griefs and joys.
She swings a wicked pencil!
In forms of cube and octagon,
Ignoring technicalities,
She splashes her impressions on,
In broadest generalities.
She paints no view of moonlit glen,
No landscape, green and grassy;
Her subjects run to gentlemen
And ladies, in their chassis.

Her art, our connoisseurs imply,
Is all in the beholder’s eye.

To down all kings and presidents
Our Mr. Tench proposes;
His loudly uttered sentiments
Are redder than the roses.
He urges anarchism’s cause
In terms concise, but notable;
And what he says about the laws
Would scarcely pass as quotable.
He pleads that marriages be few,
While love be free, in plenty—
Which last endears him greatly to
The local cognoscenti.

His word is law, among our set,
On rules of sovietiquette.

Bores: A Hymn of Hate

I hate Bores;
They take the joy out of my life.

There are the Symptom Collectors.
They have tried every specialist once.
They go about, quoting what they said under ether;
They give readings from their fever-charts;
And they carry their cast-off appendixes with them, in bottles—
Just for old times’ sake.
They are forever showing you X-ray photographs
Of their quaint crannies and intimate inglenooks.
They say that you can never guess what they suffer,
And then they clear up all doubts.
Every doctor tells them that their case is hopeless—
I’ll say it is.

Then there are the Parlor Comedians.
They have memorized the entire series
Of history’s favorite anecdotes.
They begin by saying that they just heard a new one—
Which is the funniest line in the whole story.
They go in strongly for the kind of humor
That requires special apparatus.
They will go miles to procure an exploding cigar
Or a perforated drinking-glass.
They have a repertoire of sure-fire comedy hits:
They address all waiters as “George,”
And they love to call you on the telephone
And say, “This is Police Headquarters speaking.”
They save up all their witticisms for you,
And tell you how everyone nearly dies at them—
Nearly dies is right.

There are the Gluttons for Business.
They started on a shoe string
And worked their way up to white spats.
They are entirely self-made,
And think that everybody is clamoring for the recipe.
Their life is an open ledger;
They tell you all the inside gossip
About invoices and bills of lading,
And illustrate their talk with diagrams
Showing their increased output throughout the Middle West.
They relate heart-rending stories
Of how they haven’t had a vacation in ten years,
And how they wish they could go away for a while—
And I wish they could go away from now on.

And there are the Amateur Mediums.
They are always fooling around with the spirits.
They are constantly receiving messages from the Great Beyond
Saying Uncle Walter is well
And hopes everybody at home is the same.
They spend every night
Being warned, in dreams, of their friends’ deaths.
There is nothing that they can’t worm out of a ouija board.
They are so messy around the house;
They are always tipping tables
And sitting around in circles, with the lights out.
They are forever seeing things and hearing knocks,
And they just know they have clairvoyant minds—
If any.

I hate Bores;
They take the joy out of my life.

With Best Wishes

GLAD Christmas Day once more has come—
There’s little novelty in that.
It’s welcomed eagerly by some,
Which isn’t to be marveled at.
Their stockings hold a house and lot
(I hope you gather what I mean),
A picturesquely furnished yacht,
A next year’s model limousine,
A sable wrap of graceful cut,
A sheaf of cheques for vast amounts;
It’s not the thought that matters, but
The gift which goes with it that counts.

But I’ll get a multitude of seasonable cards,
A bowl full of lily bulbs, approaching their decease;
A pair of gilded shoe-trees, with appropriate regards,
And a leather-bound “Evangeline,” with colored frontispiece.

It’s scarcely any wonder that
The season finds me all unmoved,
For Father Christmas leaves me flat—
Step-Father Christmas, it has proved.
’Twas ever thus—from early youth
I’ve seen my hopes decay, because
Too soon I learned the bitter truth:
There isn’t any Santa Claus.
Each Yuletide mocks my touching trust;
Though give and let give is my plea,
It’s Christmas Day for some, but just
December twenty-fifth for me.

For I’ll get a paper-weight, to crush my Christmas cheer,
A hand-painted needle-case, a brace of button-hooks,
A host of cordial wishes for a prosperous new year,
And a holiday edition of the “Rubaiyat,” de luxe.

I’ve often heard that some there are—
How hard such tales are to believe!—
To prove that costlier by far
It is to give than to receive.
On Christmas they present their friends
With motor cars, and pearls in strings,
And blocks of stock with dividends,
And other useful little things.
Though I have no such benefits,
I sing the Christmas spirit’s praise.
I know the giver’s thrill—for it’s
A poor Yule which won’t work both ways.

So I’ll give a laundry bag, of chintz refined, yet gay;
A tooth-brush container of a fanciful design,
A flock of timely greetings for a snappy Christmas Day,
And a highly colored copy of “That Old Sweetheart of Mine.”

Invictus

FARTHEST am I from perfection’s heights,
Faulty am I as I well could be,
Still I insist on my share of rights.
When I am dead, think this of me:
Though I have uttered the words “Yea, bo,”
Though I use “ain’t” to get a laugh,
Though I am wont to explain “Let’s go,”
Though I say “You don’t know the half,”—
Black though my record as darkest jet,
Give me, I beg, my devil’s due;
Only remember, I’ve never yet
Said, “How’s the world been treating you?”

“What could be sweeter?” I fondly muse;
“You said a mouthful,” I confess;
Witnesses testify that I use
“Yes, indeed,” in times of stress;
“Oh, it’s a great life,” I loudly claim—
“If you don’t weaken,” I amend;
“I’ll tell the world” is my middle name;
“Well, how’s the boy?” I greet a friend.
While I acknowledge each grave defect,
Still I am master of my fate—
All that I ask you is, Recollect
I never said, “I’m here to state.”

“Yours till hell freezes,” I sign my mail;
“I’ll say it is,” I coyly cry;
“What’s the good word?” is my cheery hail;
Bidding farewell, I say “Bye-bye”;
I demand, “How do you get that way?”
“Oh, have a heart,” is all my plea;
Speaking of oysters, I sadly say,
“I like them, but they don’t like me.”

Humbly I own to each one of these,
Yet I atone for all my slips;
Heap me a measure of credit, please—
“Kiddie” has never passed my lips.

Song of the Open Country

When lights are low, and the day has died,
I sit and dream of the countryside.

Where sky meets earth at the meadow’s end,
I dream of a clean and wind-swept space
Where each tall tree is a stanch old friend,
And each frail bud turns a trusting face.
A purling brook, with each purl a pray’r,
To the bending grass its secret tells;
While, softly borne on the scented air,
Comes the far-off chime of chapel bells.
A tiny cottage I seem to see,
In its quaint old garden set apart;
And a Sabbath calm steals over me,
While peace dwells deep in my brooding heart.

And I thank whatever gods look down
That I am living right here in town.

The Passionate Freudian to His Love

Only name the day, and we’ll fly away
In the face of old traditions,
To a sheltered spot, by the world forgot,
Where we’ll park our inhibitions.
Come and gaze in eyes where the lovelight lies
As it psychoanalyzes,
And when once you glean what your fancies mean
Life will hold no more surprises.
When you’ve told your love what you’re thinking of
Things will be much more informal;
Through a sunlit land we’ll go hand-in-hand,
Drifting gently back to normal.

While the pale moon gleams, we will dream sweet dreams,
And I’ll win your admiration,
For it’s only fair to admit I’m there
With a mean interpretation.
In the sunrise glow we will whisper low
Of the scenes our dreams have painted,
And when you’re advised what they symbolized
We’ll begin to feel acquainted.
So we’ll gaily float in a slumber boat
Where subconscious waves dash wildly;
In the stars’ soft light, we will say good-night—
And “good-night!” will put it mildly.

Our desires shall be from repressions free—
As it’s only right to treat them.
To your ego’s whims I will sing sweet hymns,
And ad libido repeat them.
With your hand in mine, idly we’ll recline
Amid bowers of neuroses,
While the sun sinks rest in the great red west
We will sit and match psychoses.
So come dwell a while on that distant isle
In the brilliant tropic weather;
Where a Freud in need is a Freud indeed,
We’ll be always Jung together.

The Drama: A Hymn of Hate

I hate the Drama;
It cuts in on my sleep.

There is the Clean Play;
The one you take Aunt Etta to see
After a day’s sightseeing in the financial district.
The hero is the man from Back Home,
With the blameless life and the creaseless trousers—
A real rough rhinestone.
He may not be so strong on grammar,
But he loves children and sleeping outdoors.
The heroine sneers at him in Act I,
But after he has shown up the effete aristocracy,
And received news that they’ve struck oil
Back in the Little Marigold well,
She listens to reason.
And when the curtain falls at eleven o’clock,
They are starting out for the Great, Clean West together—
Three hours too late.

Then there is the Comedy of Manners;
The manners provide most of the comedy.
It is all about the goings-on in titled circles—
How Her Grace’s handkerchief
Was found in Sir Arthur’s diggings.
Tea flows like water,
Butlers are everywhere,
And there is practically no stint to the epigrams
About there being two kinds of husbands:
Your own, and the kind that is in love with you.
Everybody stands about,
Gesticulating with cucumber sandwiches,
And saying, “Oh, Lord Cyril, what a cynic you are!”
There is always a little country ingenue
Who tearfully goes back home in the last act,
Declaring that those society people are all rotten—
She said it.

There is the Farthest North performance
Of the Play That Makes You Think—
Makes you think that you should have gone to the movies.
It is translated from the Norwegian;
They might just as well give it to us in the original.
All the lighting is dim
So that the actors’ faces can scarcely be distinguished,
Which is doubtless all for the best.
The heroine is invariably Misunderstood—
Probably because of her accent.
She is a regular little Glad Girl,
Always falling in love with an innocent bystander,
Or finding that she has married her uncle by mistake,
Or going out into the night and slamming the door.
And things come to a rousing climax
In a nice, restful suicide, or a promising case of insanity.
You tell ’em, Ibsen; you’ve got the Scandinavian rights.

And there is the Allegorical Drama;
It becomes as sounding brass or a tinkling symbol.
The critics can always find subtle shades of meaning in it—
The triumph of mind over Maeterlinck.
The actors play the parts
Of Light, Joy, Beauty, and Imagination,
While the audience represent Ennui and Bewilderment.
The leading character is searching for Happiness.
And after hunting through four acts, twenty-seven scenes,
And a company of three hundred, exclusive of stage-hands,
He finally discovers it at home—
Would to Heaven he had looked there in the first place!

I hate the Drama;
It cuts in on my sleep.

Parties: A Hymn of Hate

I Hate Parties;
They bring out the worst in me.

There is the Novelty Affair,
Given by the woman
Who is awfully clever at that sort of thing.
Everybody must come in fancy dress;
There are always eleven Old-Fashioned Girls,
And fourteen Hawaiian gentlemen
Wearing the native costume
Of last season’s tennis clothes, with a wreath around the neck.

The hostess introduces a series of clean, home games;
Each participant is given a fair chance
To guess the number of seeds in a cucumber,
Or thread a needle against time,
Or see how many names of wild flowers he knows.
Ice cream in trick formations,
And punch like Volstead used to make
Buoy up the players after the mental strain.
You have to tell the hostess that it’s a riot,
And she says she’ll just die if you don’t come to her next party—
If only a guarantee went with that!

Then there is the Bridge Festival.
The winner is awarded an arts-and-crafts hearth-brush,
And all the rest get garlands of hothouse raspberries.
You cut for partners
And draw the man who wrote the game.
He won’t let bygones be bygones;
After each hand
He starts getting personal about your motives in leading clubs.
And one word frequently leads to another.

At the next table
You have one of those partners
Who says it is nothing but a game, after all.
He trumps your ace
And tries to laugh it off.
And yet they shoot men like Elwell.

There is the Day in the Country;
It seems more like a week.
All the contestants are wedged into automobiles,
And you are allotted the space between two ladies
Who close in on you.
The party gets a nice early start,
Because everybody wants to make a long day of it—
They get their wish.
Everyone contributes a basket of lunch;
Each person has it all figured out
That no one else will think of bringing hard-boiled eggs.

There is intensive picking of dogwood,
And no one is quite sure what poison ivy is like;
They find out by the next day.
Things start off with a rush.
Everybody joins in the old songs,
And points out cloud effects,
And puts in a good word for the color of the grass.
But after the first fifty miles,
Nature doesn’t go over so big,
And singing belongs to the lost arts.
There is a slight spurt on the homestretch,
And everyone exclaims over how beautiful the lights of the city look—
I’ll say they do.

And there is the informal little Dinner Party;
The lowest form of taking nourishment.
The man on your left draws diagrams with a fork,
Illustrating the way he is going to have the new sun-parlor built on;
And the one on your right
Explains how soon business conditions will be better, and why.

When the more material part of the evening is over,
You have your choice of listening to the Harry Lauder records,
Or having the hostess hem you in
And show you the snapshots of the baby they took last summer.
Just before you break away,
You mutter something to the host and hostess
About sometime soon you must have them over—
Over your dead body.

I Hate Parties;
They bring out the worst in me.

Love Song

Suppose we two were cast away
On some deserted strand,
Where in the breeze the palm trees sway—
A sunlit wonderland;
Where never human footstep fell,
Where tropic love-birds woo,
Like Eve and Adam we could dwell,
In paradise, for two.
Would you, I wonder, tire of me
As sunny days went by,
And would you welcome joyously
A steamer? … So would I.

Suppose we sought bucolic ways
And led the simple life,
Away—as runs the happy phrase—
From cities’ toil and strife.
There you and I could live alone,
And share our hopes and fears.
A small-town Darby and his Joan,
We’d face the quiet years.
I wonder, would you ever learn
My charms could pall on you,
And would you let your fancy turn
To others? … I would, too.

Between us two (suppose once more)
Had rolled the bounding deep;
You journeyed to a foreign shore,
And left me here to weep.
I wonder if you’d be the same,
Though we were far apart,
And if you’d always bear my name
Engraved upon your heart.
Or would you bask in other smiles,
And, charmed by novelty,
Forget the one so many miles
Away? … That goes for me.

Idyl

Think of the things that can never come true—
Save in the shadowy country of dreams.
Think of what might be, for me and for you,
Could we but shatter the world’s sorry schemes.
Think of our own little vine-covered nest;
Each day, at sunset, I’d wait for you there,
Down by the gate, in the glow of the west,
Dressed all in white, with a rose in my hair.
Think of a chair, softly-cushioned and wide;
Think of a hearth, where the red firelight dies;
Think of me sitting there, close by your side,
Reading the stories writ deep in your eyes.
Think of the years, like an unending song,
Think of a quiet we never have known.
While, all forgotten, the world rolls along,
Think of us two, in a world of our own.

Now that you’ve thought of it seriously—
Isn’t it great that it never can be?

Movies: A Hymn of Hate

I hate Movies;
They lower my vitality.

There is the Great Spectacle.
No press-agent admits
That it is the most remarkable picture ever made.
The story is taken from history,
But the scenario writer smoothes things over a little,
And makes Cleopatra Antony’s wife,
Or has Salome marry John the Baptist,
So that you can bring the kiddies.
The management compiles vital statistics
About the size of the cast:
How the entire population of California
Takes part in the battle scenes;
And where the beads worn by the star would reach
If placed end to end.
The audience sits panting
And says, “Think what it must have cost to produce it!”
Think what could have been saved by not producing it!

Then there is the Picture with Sex Appeal;
The appeal is still unanswered.
The production goes to show
That bad taste, off the screen,
Is still in its infancy.
It seeks to reveal the depths to which society has fallen,
And it proves its point.
It gives glimpses of Night Life in the Great City:
The revelers are shown wearing fancy paper hats,
And marching in lockstep around the table,
And shamelessly performing the two-step.
The characters are always driving home in motors
To the Public Library, or Senator Clark’s house.
The interiors are designed
By the man who decorates dentists’ waiting-rooms.
The star is a prominent vampire
Who is a nice, sweet girl when she is at home,
And supports an indulgent husband
In the style to which he has become accustomed;
The wages of sin is $3,500 a week.

There is the High Art Production:
They charge three dollars a seat for it—
That’s where they get the “high.”
The photography is always tricky;
The actors seem to be enveloped in a dense fog,
And that goes for the plot, too.
There is some idea of an allegorical strain running through it,
So that, whenever things are beginning to get good,
And the heroine is just about to fall,
The scene changes
To a panorama of storm clouds,
Or a still-life study of apple blossoms,
Or a view of Hong-Kong harbor by moonlight.
Every few minutes, there is a close-up of the star
Registering one of her three expressions.
The sub-titles offer positive proof
That there is a place where bad metaphors go when they die.
The critics agree unanimously
That the picture removes all doubt
As to whether movies should be classed among the arts—
Removes all doubt is right.

And there is the News of the Week.
It is assembled on the principle
That no news is good news.
It shows all the big events in current history:
The paperweight manufacturers’ convention in Des Moines;
The procession of floats during Anti-Litter Week in Topeka;
And the sailors of the U. S. S. Mississippi
Grouped to form the words “E Pluribus Unum.”
There is always a view of a wrecked schooner,
Enabling the pianist to oblige with “Asleep in the Deep.”
When they have a chance to show a picture of a fire
They color it a mean shade of red.
Before you can get a good look at the event before you,
The scene changes to a new one
Leaving the fate of the people in the last picture hanging—
It’s too good for them.

I Hate Movies;
They lower my vitality.

To My Dog

I often wonder why on earth
You rate yourself so highly;
A shameless parasite, from birth
You’ve lived the life of Reilly.
No claims to fame distinguish you;
Your talents are not many;
You’re constantly unfaithful to
Your better self—if any.
Yet you believe, with faith profound,
The world revolves about you;
May I point out, it staggered ’round
For centuries without you?

In beauty, you’re convinced you lead,
While others only follow.
You think you look like Wallace Reid,
Or, at the least, Apollo.
The fatal charms with which you’re blest,
You fancy, spell perfection;
The notion, may I not suggest,
Is open to correction?
An alien streak your tail betrays;
Your ears aren’t what they would be;
Your mother was—forgive the phrase—
No better than she should be.

One can but feel your gaiety
Is somewhat over-hearty;
You take it on yourself to be
The life of every party.
In bearing, while no doubt sincere,
You’re frankly, too informal.
And mentally, I sometimes fear,
You’re slightly under normal.
The least attention turns your brain,
Repressions slip their tether;
Pray spare your friends the nervous strain
And pull yourself together!

You take no thought for others’ good
In all your daily dealings,
I ask you, as a mother would,
Where are your finer feelings?
I think I’ve seldom run across
A life so far from lawful;
Your manners are a total loss,
Your morals, something awful.
Perhaps you’ll ask, as many do,
“What I endure your thrall for?”
’Twas ever thus—it’s nothing new
That women always fall for.

Absence

I never thought that heav’n would lose its blue
And sullen storm-clouds mask the gentle sky;
I never thought the rose’s velvet hue
Would pale and sicken, though we said good-by.
I never dreamed the lark would hush its note
As day succeeded ever-drearier day,
Nor knew the song that swelled the robin’s throat
Would fade to silence, when you went away.
I never knew the sun’s irradiant beams
Upon the brooding earth no more would shine,
Nor thought that only in my mocking dreams
Would happiness that once I knew be mine.
I never thought the slim moon, mournfully,
Would shroud her pallid self in murky night.
Dear heart, I never thought these things would be—
I never thought they would, and I was right.

Lyric

How the arrogant iris would wither and fade
If the soft summer dew never fell,
And the timid arbutus that hides in the shade
Would no longer make fragrant the dell!
All the silver-flecked fishes would languish and die
Were it not for the foam-spangled streams;
Little brooks could not flow, without rain from the sky;
Nor a poet get on without dreams.
If the blossoms refused their pale honey, the bees
Must in idleness hunger and pine;
While the moss cannot live, when it’s torn from the trees,
Nor the waxen-globed mistletoe twine.
Were it not for the sunshine, the birds wouldn’t sing,
And the heavens would never be blue.
But of all Nature’s works, the most wonderful thing
Is how well I get on without you.

Song for the First of the Month

Money cannot fill our needs,
Bags of gold have little worth;
Thoughtful ways and kindly deeds
Make a heaven here on earth.
Riches do not always score,
Loving words are better far.
Just one helpful act is more
Than a gaudy motor car.
Happy thoughts contentment bring
Crabbed millionaires can’t know;
Money doesn’t mean a thing—
Try to tell the butcher so!

None can stretch his life an hour
Though he offer boundless wealth;
Money, spite of all its pow’r,
Cannot purchase ruddy health.
Simple pleasures are the best,
Riches bring but misery,
Homely hearts are happiest,
Joy laughs loud at poverty.
Pity those in Mammon’s thrall,
Poor, misguided souls are they.
Money’s nothing, after all—
Make the grocer think that way!

Greatest minds the world has known
All agree that gold is dross.
Man can’t live by wealth alone;
Bank books are a total loss.
Banish strife and greed and gloom,
Throw off money’s harsh control,
Sow good deeds, and watch them bloom—
Hyacinths, to feed the soul.
Hoard no pelf, lest moth and rust
Do their work and leave you flat.
Money? It is less than dust—
Laugh the landlord off with that!

Fulfilment

I do not sit and sigh for wealth untold,
It never thrusts itself into my schemes;
I shrink from all your piles of clanking gold—
Better my sparkling hoard of golden dreams.
A life of limousined and jeweled ease
Is but a round of fathomless ennui.
Your motor cars, your pearls, your sables—these
Are naught to me.
Better a homely flat in Harlem’s wilds
Than costly living’s spurious benefits;
Better a simple butter-cake at Childs’
Than caviar and stalled ox at the Ritz.
Your unearned gold, to me, is shot with flaws;
A life of honest toil I’d make my lot—
Which really makes it very nice, because
It’s what I’ve got.

Lynn Fontanne

Dulcy, take our gratitude.
All your words are gold ones,
Mistress of the platitude,
Queen of all the old ones.
You, at last, are something new
’Neath the theatre’s dome. I’d
Mention to the cosmos, you
Swing a wicked bromide.
Heroines we’ve known, to date,
Scattered scintillations
(Courtesy the Wilde estate)
Through their conversations.
Polished line and sparkling jest—
They’ve provided plenty.
Dulcy’s bromides brought us rest—
Dulcy far niente.

To Marjorie Rambeau

In “Daddy’s Gone A-Hunting”

If all the tears you shed so lavishly
Were gathered, as they left each brimming eye,
And were collected in a crystal sea,
The envious ocean would curl up and dry—
So awful in its mightiness, that lake,
So fathomless, that clear and salty deep.
For, oh, it seems your gentle heart must break,
To see you weep.

We try to tell ourselves it isn’t true,
We strive to feel that dawn must follow dark,
We strain to hold the thought that, off-stage, you
Are happy as the widely-mentioned lark.
But, though you wring our feelings to their cores,
Our devastated hearts you seem to keep.
For, oh, we pack the theatre to its doors
To see you weep.

“Christmas, 1921”

I do not ask you for presents rare,
Other-world trove of forgotten metals;
Orchids that opened to jungle air,
Tropical hate in their writhing petals;
Onyx and ebony, black as pain,
Carved with a patience beyond believing;
Perfumes, to harry the startled brain;
Laces that women have died in weaving;
Cool-tinted pearls from the ocean, where
Grotures of dolorous green regret them.
I do not ask you for presents rare.—
Dearest, I know that I wouldn’t get them.

Give me your love, on this Christmas Day.
Give me your thoughts, when the chimes are ringing.
Send me the happier along my way.
Deep in my soul let your words be singing.
Give me your wishes, as bells sound clear,
Charming the air with their golden measure.
Give me your hopes for the unborn year.
Fill up my heart with a secret treasure.
Give me the things that you long to say.
All of your tenderest dreams unfetter.
Give me your love, on this Christmas Day.—
But come across, please, when times get better.

Marilyn Miller

FROM the alley’s gloom and chill
Up to fame danced Sally,
Which was nice for her, but still
Rough upon the alley.
How it must regret her wiles,
All her ways and glances,
Now the theatre owns her smiles,
Sallies, songs, and dances.
Ever onward Sally goes—
Life’s one thing that’s certain.
O’er the end of other shows
Let us draw a curtain.
Their untimely ends are sad,
But they stood no chances,
For, you see, they never had
Sally’s songs and dances.

Books: A Hymn of Hate

I Hate Books:
They tire my eyes

THERE is the Account of Happy Days in Far Tahiti;
The booklet of South Sea Island resorts.
After his four weeks in the South Seas,
The author’s English gets pretty rusty
And he has to keep dropping into the native dialect.
He implies that his greatest hardship
Was fighting off the advances of the local girls,
But the rest of the book
Was probably founded on fact.
You can pick up a lot of handy information
On how to serve poi,
And where the legend of the breadfruit tree got its start,
And how to take kava or let it alone.
The author says it’s the only life
And as good as promises
That sometime he is going to throw over his writing,
And go end his days with Laughing Sea-pig, the half-caste Knock-out—
Why wait?

THEN there is the Little Book of Whimsical Essays;
Not a headache in a libraryful
The author comes right out and tells his favorite foods,
And how much he likes his pipe,
And what his walking-stick means to him—
A thrill on every page.
The essays clean up all doubt
On what the author feels when riding in the subway,
Or strolling along the Palisades.
The writer seems to be going ahead on the idea
That it isn’t such a bad old world, after all;
He drowses along
Under the influence of Pollyanesthetics.
No one is ever known to buy the book;
You find it on the guest room night-table,
Or win it at a Five Hundred Party,
Or someone gives it to you for Easter
And follows that up by asking you how you liked it—
Say it with raspberries!

THERE is the novel of Primitive Emotions;
The Last Word in Unbridled Passions—
Last but not leashed.
The author writes about sex
As if he were the boy who got up the idea.
The hero and heroine may be running wild in the Sahara,
Or camping informally on a desert island,
Or just knocking around the city,
But the plot is always the same—
They never quite make the grade.
The man turns out to be the son of a nobleman,
Or the woman the world’s greatest heiress,
And they marry and go to live together—
That can’t hold much novelty for them.
It is but a question of time till the book is made into a movie,
Which is no blow to its writer.
People laugh it off
By admitting that it may not be the highest form of art;
But then, they plead, the author must live—
What’s the big idea?

AND then there is the Realistic Novel;
Five hundred pages without a snicker.
It is practically an open secret
That the book is two dollars’ worth of the author’s own experiences,
And that if he had not been through them,
It would never have been written,
Which would have been all right with me.
It presents a picture of quiet family life—
Of how little Rosemary yearns to knife Grandpa,
And Father wishes Mother were cold in her grave,
And Bobby wants to marry his big brother.
The author’s idea of action
Is to make one of his characters spill the cereal.
The big scene of the book
Is the heroine’s decision to make over her old taffeta.
All the characters are in a bad way;
They have a lot of trouble with their suppressions.
The author is constantly explaining that they are all being stifled—
I wish to God he’d give them the air!

I Hate Books:
They tire my eyes

Fragment

Why should we set these hearts of ours above
The rest, and cramp them in possession’s clutch?
Poor things, we gasp and strain to capture love,
And in our hands, it powders at our touch.
We turn the fragrant pages of the past,
Mournful with scent of passion’s faded flow’rs,
On every one we read, “Love cannot last,”—
So how could ours?

It is the quest that thrills, and not the gain,
The mad pursuit, and not the cornering:
Love caught is but a drop of April rain,
But bloom upon the moth’s translucent wing.
Why should you dare to hope that you and I
Could make love’s fitful flash a lasting flame?
Still, if you think it’s only fair to try—
Well, I am game.

Figures in Popular Literature: The Sheik

The desert chieftain here behold,
The Dempsey of the Nile.
He knocks the lady readers cold
And cramps their husbands’ style.
The heroine reels back for more.
They play like happy kids—
He tells his love, then knocks her for
A row of pyramids.

She revels in his gallant deeds;
Her passions higher mount
Each time he languidly proceeds
To drop her for the count.
They marry in the end—they do
In all such compositions—
And now, no doubt, he’ll knock her through
Another twelve editions.

So if you’d knock the ladies dead,
Just use your right and go ahead.

Figures in Popular Literature: The Flapper

The playful flapper here we see,
The fairest of the fair.
She’s not what Grandma used to be—
You might say, au contraire.
Her girlish ways may make a stir,
Her manners cause a scene,
But there is no more harm in her
Than in a submarine.

She nightly knocks for many a goal
The usual dancing men.
Her speed is great, but her control
Is something else again.
All spotlights focus on her pranks,
All tongues her prowess herald,
For which she well may render thanks
To God and Scott Fitzgerald.

Her golden rule is plain enough—
Just get them young and treat them rough.

Chantey

A wet sheet and a straining sail,
And a sea of shifting blue;
A wide sky and a rousing gale,
And joy in the heart of you;
A clean line, where the sky hangs low
And a seagull soars and dips;
And the old voice that bids men go—
Go down to the sea in ships.

So go and sail the gold sea, the bold sea, the cold sea,
The waving, craving, raving sea that’s fringed with silken foam;
Oh, go and sail the green sea, the keen sea, the mean sea—
But if it’s all the same to you, I’ll stick around at home.

The swift turn of the night-wind’s whim,
And the twang of hempen strings;
The sharp snap of the halyards slim,
And the spray that cuts and stings.
The wild chorus the breezes hum,
And the waves that prowl and creep;
And the old voice that bids men come—
Come over the tameless deep.

So go and sail the white sea, the light sea, the bright sea,
The dashing, crashing, smashing sea, that dances in the gale;
Go on and sail the sad sea, the bad sea, the mad sea—
But if it’s just the same to you, I’d rather be in jail.

Moral Tales for the Young [1]

Maude, the brightest of the sex,
Forged her daddy’s name to checks,
Took them to the local banks,
Cashed them, with a smile of thanks.
All the money came in handy—
Maudie was so fond of candy!
Weight she gained in way affrighting,
So she’s given up her writing.

Save the money, when you forge;
Little ladies do not gorge.

Don, the little apple-cheek,
Sold his aunt’s blue-ribbon Peke,
Sneaked it out of Auntie’s house,
Hidden in his sailor blouse.
Donald planned to spend his earnings
Gratifying all his yearnings.
But the chance for pleasure slipped him,
For the doggie’s buyer gypped him.

If they can’t complete the deal,
Nicer children do not steal.

Valentines

Princess Mary and Viscount Lascelles

Here behold, and likewise lo,
Princess Mary and her beau.
Bright her cheek with maiden blush;—
Shall we say a royal flush?
How we’ve watched their love’s ascents
In the Sunday supplements!
Blessings for the happy pair;
For their photographs—the air!

Mr. David Wark Griffith

Look, and you will surely find
Right above, the Master Mind.
(Just a nickname of his own
Which he worked up all alone.)
He it was who made, they say,
Movies what they are today;
This the goal for which he’s tried—
Lord, I hope he’s satisfied!

Mr. David Belasco

Often in the local press
On your kindness you lay stress.
Love’s the basis of your art,
So you say—that is, in part.
Frequently you tell us of
How devotedly you love
Actors, public, critics, too …
Echo answers, “Yes, you do.”

Mr. Calvin Coolidge

“Ah,” we said; and eke “At last.
Things won’t be as in the past;
Once vice-presidents were nil,
But our Fighting Calvin will
All such precedents destroy.”
“Ah,” we said; and “Atta boy!” …
Now we wonder dolefully
What’s become of Calvin C.?

Dr. Frank Crane

Daily you distribute praise
‘Mong clean books and wholesome plays.
Honest toil and hard-earned gold,
Kindness to the weak and old;
Where would all the virtues be
Without such publicity?
Wealth untold you’re paid, per line.
Won’t you be my Valentine?

Mr. Avery Hopwood

How you must have loved, when small,
Chalking words upon a wall!
“Ladies’ Night” we owe to you,
“Getting Gertie’s Garter,” too.
Gaily gath’ring royalties
On your bedroom phantasies,
Ever heavier grows your purse
As you go from bed to worse.

Mr. Florenz Ziegfeld

Still we’re groggy from the blow
Dealt us—by the famous Flo;
After 1924,
He announces, nevermore
Will his shows our senses greet—
At a cost of five per seat.
Hasten, Time, your onward drive—
Welcome, 1925!

Mr. John Wanamaker

On the advertising page
Scintillates our dry goods sage.
Not a text that Honest John
Cannot write a sermon on.
Readers live from day to day
Just to see what he will say.
“Have you seen his last?” they cry.
“Would to God I had,” say I.

The Far-Sighted Muse

Dark though the clouds, they are silver-lined;
(This is the stuff that they like to read.)
If Winter comes, Spring is right behind;
(This is the stuff that the people need.)
Smile, and the World will smile back at you;
Aim with a grin, and you cannot miss;
Laugh off your woes, and you won’t feel blue.
(Poetry pays when it’s done like this.)

Whatever is, is completely sweet;
(This is the stuff that will bring in gold.)
Just to be living’s a perfect treat;
(This is the stuff that will knock them cold.)
How could we, any of us, be sad?—
Always our blessings outweigh our ills;
Always there’s something to make us glad.
(This is the way you can pay your bills.)

Everything’s great, in this good old world;
(This is the stuff they can always use.)
God’s in His heaven, the hill’s dew-pearled;
(This will provide for the baby’s shoes.)
Hunger and War, do not mean a thing;—
Everything’s rosy, where’er we roam;
Hark, how the little birds gaily sing!
(This is what fetches the bacon home.)

Figures in Popular Literature: The Drab Heroine

There was a time, as doubtless you’re
Enabled to recall,
When heroines of literature
Were not like this at all.
Their hair was heaped in glinting curls,
Their forms were wondrous fair,
And when it came to sex, the girls
Admittedly were there.

To-day, toward woolen lingerie
The lady’s thoughts are turned,
And sex is in its infancy
So far as she’s concerned.
A kitchen drudge, whom all ignore,
She leads a life entrancing
As Cinderella’s was, before
She took up ballroom dancing.

Abandon hope, and learn to cook,
And you will figure in a book.

Paging Saint Patrick

The good Saint Patrick, in his day,
Performed a worthy act:
He up and drove the snakes away,
With more technique than tact.
Could he descend from realms above
And roam about New York,
He’d find it reminiscent of
The good old days in Cork.
The snakes he knew could never tie
The brand our village has—
The kind that daily multiply
And thrive on tea and jazz.

Should he his tales of snakes relate
We’d strive to hide a laugh;
For, though the saint was wise and great,
He didn’t know the half.
Where’er he’d go, to dine or dance,
Or lunch, or tea, or sup,
The saint would have a splendid chance
To do some cleaning up.
Could he but leave his present star,
He’d see that things were changed;—
How sad such little visits are
Not easily arranged!

Mood

Unless I yield my love to you, you swear
In strangely distant countries must you dwell;
Denied this heart of mine, you could not bear
These dear, familiar scenes we’ve loved so well.
To-morrows that will come, you could not face
With only pain to bear you company,
Among the whispering memories of this place,
The little, intimate things that speak of me.

Where mighty mountains rear their cruel height,
The world between us, would you dwell, apart;
Where curious peace, that comes with tropic night,
Answers the bitter question of your heart.
The lilac bush, that bends with bloom in May,
The winding path, the arbor where we sat,
These things should know you nevermore, you say—
Ah, love, if I could only count on that!

Triolets

Herewith I send you my heart.
Marking it “Fragile—don’t break it.”
Rather a radical start—
Herewith I send you my heart;
Take it, I beg, in good part
(That is, assuming you’ll take it).
Herewith I send you my heart,
Marking it “Fragile—don’t break it.”

Take me, or let me alone—
What, after all, does it matter?
Ever my feelings you’ve known;
Take me, or let me alone—
Though, I might readily own,
I’d recommend you the latter.
Take me, or let me alone—
What, after all, does it matter?

Sweet, I have waited too long;
Heedless and wanton I’ve tarried.
Silenced forever my song—
Sweet, I have waited too long,
Bitter the hemlock, and strong—
Now you have gone and got married!
Sweet, I have waited too long;
Heedless and wanton, I’ve tarried.

Figures in Popular Literature: The Western Hero

This hero ranks among the best—
He’s Nature’s rugged child.
You’ve heard about the woolly West?
’Twas he who drove it wild.
Observe that he is dressed to kill
(Forgive the pun, I pray),
In pranks like this he finds a thrill—
He’s simply full of play.

In his revolver terrors lurk;
His aim’s a deadly one.
Could Annie Oakley see his work,
She’d throw away her gun.
He trifles not with woman’s love,
In spite of his virility,
For he’s a charter member of
The natural nobility.

He shoots to kill and aims to please;
Our books are filled with such as these.

The Younger Set: A Hymn of Hate

I hate the Younger Set:
They harden my arteries.

There are the Boy Authors;
The ones who are going to put belles lettres on their feet.
Every night before they go to sleep
They kneel down and ask H. L. Mencken
To bless them and make them good boys.
They are always carrying volumes with home-cut pages,
And saying that after all, there is only one Remy de Gourmont;
Which doesn’t get any dissension out of me.
They shrink from publicity
As you or I would
From the gift of a million dollars.
At the drop of a hat
They will give readings from their works—
In department stores,
Or grain elevators,
Or ladies’ dressing-rooms.
It is pretty hard to get them to show you their work;
Sometimes you even have to ask them to.
They are constantly backing you into corners,
And asking you to glance over some little things
That they just dashed off in a spare year—
Read ’em and weep!

Then there are the Male Flappers;
The Usual Dancing Men.
They can drink one straight Orange Pekoe after another,
And you’d never know that they had had a thing.
Four débutante parties a night is bogie for them,
And their talk is very small indeed.
They never claimed to go so big at a desk,
But they can balance a plate of chicken salad, a cup of bouillon,
And a guest-room-size napkin,
And make gestures with the other hand.
They are mean boys when the orchestra starts;
They work in so many wise steps
That you can’t tell whether it’s a waltz or a track-meet.
No one can tie them, at a charity entertainment;
They say they have often been told
That with their talent
And the way they can wear clothes
They are simply wasting their time on the amateur stage—
I can’t give them any argument on that one.

There are the Black Sheep;
The Boys with the Nasty Records.
They are always giving you glimpses of the darker side of life—
Telling you what time they got to bed yesterday morning,
And how many people passed out cold,
And where they went from there.
They virtually admit
That if they ever turned over a new leaf
The bootlegging industry would go straight to smash.
They are so inured to alcohol,
That as soon as they’ve had one cocktail,
They want to go right out and address the Senate.
They are always consulting little red notebooks,
Containing names, telephone numbers, and authors’ notes,
And it is an open secret that they have met an actress.
They tell you they know they are going the pace that kills,
And then they laugh bitterly,
And say, “But what does it matter?”—
They took the words right out of my mouth.

And there are the Heavy Thinkers;
The Gluttons for Head-Work.
They have got up a lot of novel ideas
About everybody having a right to live his own life,
And about marriage being just a few words
Muttered over you by a minister.
They say that there may be
Some Supreme Force back of the universe;
They will look into that when they get the time.
Just stand back and give them room,
And they will drop the conventions for the count.
They are pretty low in their minds about America;
They hint that its civilization
Is practically plucking at the coverlet,
And that the Other Side is the only place for intellectuals—
Bon voyage!

I hate the Younger Set;
They harden my arteries.

To Myrtilla, on Easter Day

Myrtilla’s tripping down the street,
In Easter finery.
The Easter blooms are not more sweet
And radiant-hued than she.
The rarest woodland violets were
Less fragrant than her frills,
The sunny-tinted hair of her
Would shame the daffodils.
Ah, many a heart-beat halts and skips,
And sighs pursue her way,
As down the street Myrtilla trips,
This joyous Easter Day.

Myrtilla’s tripping gaily by,
In Easter garb arrayed.
Ah, would the lads as deeply sigh
For any other maid?
The lads, they come from far and near,
When down the street she starts;
Oh, lightly step, Myrtilla dear—
Your path is strewn with hearts.
The maids are held in envy’s grips,
For they are left, forlorn,
As down the street Myrtilla trips,
This glorious Easter morn.

Ah, well may echo, sweet as love,
Her laugh’s delicious lilt,
For sure she knows the power of
Her Easter bonnet’s tilt;
A master wrought, with tender care,
Each dainty frill and flounce;
The fragrance of her, cool and rare,
Costs thirty-five per ounce.
Parisian rouge defines her lips,
And pearls her throat bedeck—
As down the street Myrtilla trips,
I hope she breaks her neck!

Figures in Popular Literature: The Glad Girl

This child of curious tendencies
To your acquaintance add.
Her smile is permanent, for she’s
The gladdest of the glad.
Come battle, famine, flood, or fire,
The cheery little one
Accepts it as her heart’s desire,
And says, “Ain’t we got fun?”

The joy of living fills her cup;
Of hope, she’s never rid.
Imagine how she’d brighten up
Your household—God forbid!
The bitter ills her fortunes send
She sprinkles smiles galore on;
It seems to me our little friend
Is something of a moron.

But if I had her author’s pelf,
I’m sure that I’d be glad, myself.

Figures in Popular Literature: The Boy Savant

Behold, in all his native state,
Dispensing truths profound,
The gifted undergraduate,
The learned campus hound.
His reading fills his youthful head
With thoughts that throb and hum,
For Nietzsche, as is often said,
Abhors a vacuum.

In lighter moments, he’s the man
That fills the flappers’ dreams;
He’d make the All-American—
If there were petting teams.
His self-regard is scarcely small,
His conservation shows it;
Just ask him anything at all—
For he’s the boy that knows it.

Oh, youth verbose, our feelings spare—
For God, for country, and forbear!

Moral Tales for the Young [2]

Little Gormley stole a purse,
Took it from his crippled nurse.
It was quite a lucky touch—
She’d been saving for a crutch.
So our hero, for a starter,
Bought a seat for “Gertie’s Garter,”
Spent in vain his gains unlawful—
For he thought the show was awful!

When you plunder Nursie’s hoard,
Spend it where you won’t be bored.

Gracie, with her golden curls,
Took her mother’s string of pearls,
Figuring—as who would not?—
It would pawn for quite a lot.
Picture, then, her indignation
When she found it imitation!
Though her grief she tries to smother,
Grace can’t feel the same towards Mother!

All pretence and sham detest;
Work for nothing but the best.

Earnest—such a little man!—
Got his family’s sedan,
Drove it over hill and dale—
Just escaped the county jail—
Maimed, in his exhilaration,
Folk of spotless reputation.
But his trip with gloom was tainted—
Now the car must be repainted!

Strive to keep the death-rate low—
Think how high repair bills go!

Poem in the American Manner

I dunno yer highfalutin’ words, but here’s th’ way it seems
When I’m peekin’ out th’ winder o’ my little House o’ Dreams;
I’ve ben lookin’ ‘roun’ this big ol’ world, as bizzy as a hive,
An’ I want t’ tell ye, neighbor mine, it’s good t’ be alive.
I’ve ben settin’ here, a-thinkin’ hard, an’ say, it seems t’ me
That this big ol’ world is jest about as good as it kin be,
With its starvin’ little babies, an’ its battles, an’ its strikes,
An’ its profiteers, an’ hold-up men —th’ dawggone little tykes!—
An’ its hungry men that fought fer us, that nobody employs,
An’ I think, “Why, shucks, we’re jest a lot o’ grown-up little boys!”
An’ I settle back, an’ light my pipe, an’ reach fer Mother’s hand,
An’ I wouldn’t swap my peace o’ mind fer nothin’ in the land;
Fer this world uv ours, that jest was made fer folks like me an’ you
Is a purty good ol’ place t’ live—say, neighbor, ain’t it true?

Thoughts

Yes, my love, I think about you
In the morning’s roseate flush;
Heavy hang the clouds, without you,
Sullen seems the dawning’s blush.
In the slender, graceful grasses,
Silver-tipped with sparkling dew,
In the woodland’s shadowy masses
All that I can see is you.

When the noon-day sun is burning,
Hot the scented air, and clear,
Then to you my thoughts are turning,
And I would that you were here.
Then I dream that, happy vagrants,
We are wandering hand in hand
Through the lanes of light and fragrance
Into Summer’s fairyland.

When the weary sun in sinking,
And the blossoms close, in rest,
Then of you, my love, I’m thinking,
As I watch the brilliant west.
When the little stars show faintly
In the Maxfield Parrish sky,
When the moon gleams, cold and saintly,
Then to you my fancies fly.

When the frightened owls are calling,
And the sombre midnight reigns,
Thick and fast the shades come crawling,
Like the thoughts of fevered brains,
When life trembles at the brink of
Death’s unfathomable deep,
You’re the last thing that I think of—
Goodness knows, I need some sleep.

Fantasy

Did we love each other, sweetest,
Skies would be forever blue;
Time would flutter by on fleetest
Wings of glittering golden hue.
Joy beyond a poet’s telling
Should we learn the meaning of;
Arcady would be our dwelling—
Did we love.

Did we love each other, darling,
Banished ugliness and gloom;
Ever sweet would pipe the starling,
Ever gay the rose would bloom.
Care and trouble could not find us,
Bliss untold would be our lot.
But, one scarcely need remind us,
We do not.

Men I’m Not Married To

No matter where my route may lie,
No matter where I repair,
In brief—no matter how or why
Or when I go, the boys are there.
On lane and byway, street and square,
On alley, path and avenue,
They seem to spring up everywhere—
The men I am not married to.

I watch them as they pass me by;
At each in wonderment I stare,
And “But for heaven’s grace,” I cry,
“There goes the guy whose name I’d bear!”
They represent no species rare,
They walk and talk as others do;
They’re fair to see—but only fair—
The men I am not married to.

I’m sure that to a mother’s eye
Is each potentially a bear;
But though at home they rank ace-high,
No change of heart could I declare.
Yet worry silvers not their hair;
They deck them not with sprigs of rue.
It’s curious how they do not care—
The men I am not married to.

L’Envoi

In fact, if they’d a chance to share
Their lot with me, a lifetime through,
They’d doubtless tender me the air—
The men I am not married to.

Woodland Song

The hothouses’ offerings, costly and rare,
Cannot ape the forget-me-not’s blue;
Blooms forced to perfection can’t hope to compare
With the lowly anemone’s hue.
The humble wild rose, unassuming and meek,
Must have stolen the setting sun’s glow;
The blushes which play o’er its delicate cheek
Are of tints that no palette may know.

No matter how lovely these flowers may be,
Gardenias and orchids look better to me.

The purple-eyed violet, fragrantly cool,
Spends its beauty extravagantly.
The waxen-white lily that sleeps on the pool
Gives its loveliness lavishly free.
Their glorious petals the poppies unfold
For whoever may happen to pass,
And Nature, made mad by the buttercups’ gold,
Flings it wantonly over the grass.

But my favorite blossoms, I’m here to aver,
Are American Beauties at five dollars per.

Rondeau [1]

It isn’t fair, to me, when you’re away.
In vain the clouds their brightest hues display,
Sweet Summer dons in vain her gladdest guise—
The vision falls but coldly on my eyes;
The sky seems draped in melancholy gray.

Though never bloomed the roses half so gay,
Though never half so radiant shone the day,
This loveliness my stubborn heart denies;
It isn’t fair.

And do you, also, sing a minor lay?
Do you to bitter yearnings fall a prey?
“Well, no,” frank Echo honestly replies,
“In fact, it is distinctly otherwise.”
And that, my dear, is why again I say
It isn’t fair.

Day-Dreams

We’d build a little bungalow,
If you and I were one,
And carefully we’d plan it, so
We’d get the morning sun.
I’d rise each day at rosy dawn
And bustle gaily down;
In evening’s cool, you’d spray the lawn
When you came back from town.

A little cook-book I should buy,
Your dishes I’d prepare;
And though they came out black and dry,
I know you wouldn’t care.
How valiantly I’d strive to learn,
Assured you’d not complain!
And if my finger I should burn,
You’d kiss away the pain.

I’d buy a little scrubbing-brush
And beautify the floors;
I’d warble gaily as a thrush
About my little chores.
But though I’d cook and sew and scrub,
A higher life I’d find;
I’d join a little women’s club
And cultivate my mind.

If you and I were one, my dear,
A model life we’d lead.
We’d travel on, from year to year,
At no increase of speed.
Ah, clear to me the vision of
The things that we should do!
And so I think it best, my love,
To string along as two.

Figures in Popular Literature: The Great Lover

I’m sure you’ve met this lad before;
His work is fast, though rough.
He feels that all is fair in war—
In love, it’s fair enough.
His tale the Vice-Suppressor takes,
And drinks in every word
(A single swallow never makes
A Summer, we have heard).

Our hero lived in ages gone—
The days of bright romance.
We read about his goings-on
And sigh, “So this is France!”
You must concede, the boy was good
Among the local ladies;
But his intentions toward them would
Not pave the streets of Hades.

How sweet to read of days of old
When knights, to say the least, were bold!

Rosemary [1]

Ah, no, I dare not lose myself in dreams
Of that dead day we ne’er shall know again;
So pitifully brief a while it seems,
So sharp the thought of you, as you were then.
The poignant memories of little things—
A flower in your coat, a frock I wore;
The wistful autumns, and the troubling springs—
I dare not let them come to me once more.

The tender gloamings, when we two would stray
Where locusts hung their frothy blooms above;
The violets—like my eyes, you used to say;
The rustic bridge, where first you spoke of love;
The words we whispered, while the summer breeze
Fluttered the grasses with its scented breath;
Ah, no, I dare not summon thoughts like these;
I’m so afraid I’d laugh myself to death.

Song [1]

And shall we build a little nest
In Arcady, in Arcady,
Where we can settle down and rest
In sweet security;
A place where sunbeams cast their spell,
And shadows play, and shadows play,
Where you and I and Love can dwell
Forever and a day?

And shall we go there, you and I,
In poppy time, in poppy time,
When fluffy cloudlets dot the sky
And clustered roses climb?
And shall we watch the seasons wane,
And come and go, and come and go,
And welcome April’s golden rain,
And hail December’s snow?

And will no other ever find
Our garden spot, our garden spot?
And shall we leave the world behind
And count it well forgot?
There boundless peace can come to us,
But trouble can’t, but trouble can’t.
And shall we live forever thus?
You bet your life we shan’t.

Summer Resorts: A Hymn of Hate

I hate Summer Resorts;
They ruin my vacation.

There is the Seaside Hotel.
The booklets say that it is right on the water,
And they aren’t much over quarter-of-a-mile out of the way.
You are never at a loss for something to do;
You can go down by the waves
And watch the gentleman in sneakers
Trying out his Little Admiral water-wings,
Or you can sit on the porch
And listen to the lady in the next rocker
Explain that this is the first Summer she has ever been to a place
Where the rates were less than fifteen dollars a day.
There is always lots of excitement down on the beach—
Group photographs are constantly being taken,
And posses are being formed to find the person or persons
Who took the garters out of bathhouse number 38
And if you play your cards right,
You may be able to find a dead horseshoe crab.
The more highly-strung guests take you aside and tell you
How much they were moved to them,
And how they wish they could stay there beside it for ever and ever—
In the old church.

And then there is the place where you can get back to Nature.
Or even better.
You may find her.
When electric lights were regarded as Edison’s Folly,
And the surface of plumbing had only been scratched,
And the proprietor hasn’t got around to making any objections,
You can stand on the shore and think things over,
Otherwise you would think it was an old-fashioned rock garden.
Planted with all the flowers mentioned in Shakespeare’s works,
And a few not.
You will find a course three counties to the left.
The guests are like one big family—
Just like that.
You sit at the table with a lady from Montclair
Who tells you all the trouble that Janice has had with her toenails,
Everyone says how restful it all is,
And how it seems as if the city must be a thousand miles away—
It’s an underestimate.

There is the Synthetic Newport;
Luke-warm Dog!
The life is pretty fairly speedy;
Many of the young married set inhale right out in public,
Silver frequently changes hands after the bridge game,
And you’d almost think the cocktails were made of the real stuff—
That goes for the whole works.
Extra-marital affection is generally indulged in;
If you sit down next to your own husband,
It’s all over the country club that you are insanely jealous of him.
The revelers have their intellectual side, too;
There is scarcely one of them that hasn’t read “The Sheik.”
They are the first to concede that they are hitting things up.
They say that there won’t be a thing left of them
If they keep up the pace all Summer—
Stay with ’em, boys!

And then there is the Mountain Resort;
The Home of American Scenery.
You can go yodling up Old Baldy—
Five hundred feet above sea level—
Or you can collect postcard views of Lovers’ Leap,
To pass around among your friends on Winter evenings.
You can’t conscientiously call it a Summer
Until you get a good, clear day
When you can figure out Washington’s profile in the peaks—
You can see a better one on a two-cent stamp
Even when it’s raining.
The gossip on the porch keeps you right on the edge of your seat;
One transient tells how he is pretty sure he saw a trout jump,
And hardly has the uproar died down
Before someone else claims to have found some genuine maidenhair fern.
The guests are seldom without a kind word for the landscape,
And they have nothing but praise to offer the air—
It’s all theirs.

I hate Summer Resorts;
They ruin my vacation.

Grandfather Said It

When I was but a little thing of two, or maybe three,
My granddad—on my mother’s side—would lift me on his knee;
He’d take my thumb from out my mouth and say to me: “My dear,
Remember what I tell you when you’re choosing a career:

“Take in laundry work; cart off dust;
Drive a moving van if you must;
Shovel off the pavement when the snow lies white;
But think of your family, and please don’t write.”

When I was two I cannot say his counsel knocked me cold,
But now it all returns—for, darling, I am growing old,
And when I read the writings of the authors of today
I echo all those golden words that grandpa used to say:

“Clean out ferryboats; peddle fish;
Go be chorus men if you wish;
Rob your neighbors’ houses in the dark midnight;
But think of your families, and please don’t write.”

Monody

Slowly the roses droop and die;
(Where is the love we knew of old?)
Slowly the sun-bright days go by.
(Little white love, so cold, so cold.)
Dark are the leaves on the weary ground,
Sad are the winds in the still, gray glen;
Slowly the year goes its listless round
Over again.

Somewhere the sunbeams dance and play;
(Where is the love that used to thrill?)
Somewhere the riotous roses sway.
(Little white love, so still, so still.)
Somewhere the skies of young April shine
Bright as the heavens we prayed to then
Somewhere you’re pulling the same old line
Over again.

Somewhat Delayed Spring Song

Crocuses are springing,
Birds are lightly winging,
Corydon is singing
To his rustic lute;
Sullen winter passes,
Shepherds meet their lasses,
Tender-tinted grasses
Shoot.

All the world’s a-thrilling,
Meadow larks are shrilling,
Little brooks are trilling,
You, alone, are mute;
Why do you delay it?
Love’s a game—let’s play it,
Go ahead and say it—
Shoot!

Sonnet

Sweeter your laugh than trill of lark at dawn,
As marble richly gleams, so shines your throat.
The grace of you would shame the pale young fawn;
Rather than walk, like silken down you float.
Lighter your touch than fall of April rain;
Cooler your cheek than petal washed with dew.
Whene’er you speak, all gladness and all pain
Speak also, in the throbbing voice of you.
Like blossom on its stem is poised your head,
Wrapped closely round about with fragrant bands.
As roses’ passionate hearts, your mouth is red;
Like lilies in the wind, your long white hands.
Brighter the glance of you than summer star;
But, lady fair, how awful thick you are!

To a Lady

Lady, pretty lady, delicate and sweet,
Timorous as April, frolicsome as May,
Many are the hearts that lie beneath your feet
As they go a-dancing down the sunlit way.

Lady, pretty lady, blithe as trilling birds,
Shy as early sunbeams plays your sudden smile.
How you quaintly prattle lilting baby words,
Fluttering your helpless little hands the while!

Lady, pretty lady, bright your eyes and blue,
Who could be a-counting all the hearts they broke?
Not a man you meet that doesn’t fall for you;
Lady, pretty lady, how I hope you choke!

Memories

Once, you say, we felt love’s blisses
When the world was not so wise;
Once, you say, you knew my kisses
Under Babylonian skies.
There fulfilled our scorching passion,
There we pledged our tender vow—
Strange we meet in this cold fashion
Here and now.

Maybe you were, as you’ve stated,
Fooling round in Babylon;
Maybe you participated
In the local goings-on.
Maybe things like that befell you,
Ages past. But anyhow,
I was never there, I’ll tell you
Here and now.

Promise

Love beyond my maddest dreaming
You have sworn you’ll show to me;
You will guide me to the gleaming,
Reeling heights of ecstasy.
Dizzier joy than else could reach me,
Fiercer bliss and wilder thrill,
All of this some day you’ll teach me,
Y-e-e-s you will!

Rondeau [2]

Give me a rose, cool-petaled, virgin white,
Pure as the morning, mystical as night;
Not bold gardenias, flaunting their expense
Like courtesans, in perfumed insolence,
Nor brazen orchids, feverishly bright.

Give me no hothouse violets, cold, polite,
With lengths of costly ribbon girdled tight—
Matrons, in corseted magnificence;
Give me a rose.

One girlish blossom proffer as your mite.
Ah, lovelier by far within my sight
Than rich exotics’ glamorous pretense
Is one shy rose, sweet in its diffidence.
And then besides, my love, the price is right;
Give me a rose.

Song of the Conventions

We’d dance, with grapes in our wind-tossed hair,
And garments of swirling smoke;
We’d fling wild song to the amorous air,
‘Till the long-dead gods awoke.
Our quivering bodies, young and white,
Poised light by the brooklet’s brink,
We’d whirl and leap through the moon-mad night—
But what would the neighbors think?

We’d bid the workaday world go hang,
And idle the seasons through;
We’d pay no tribute of thought or pang
To the world that once we knew.
With hearts in ecstasy intertwined,
In languorous, sweet content,
We’d leave all worry and care behind—
But how would we pay the rent?

We’d roam the universe, hand in hand,
Through tropical climes, or cold,
And find each spot was a wonderland,
A country of pearl and gold.
Our hearts as light as the sunlit foam,
We’d voyage the oceans o’er,
With never a thought for those at home—
But wouldn’t our folks be sore?

Song [2]

Clarabelle has golden hair,
Mabel’s eyes are blue,
Nancy’s form is passing fair,
Mary’s heart is true.
Chloë’s heart has proved to be
Something else again;
Not so much on looks is she,
But she gets the men.

Doris deals in verse and prose,
Stella’s brow is high,
Martha, swift and skillful, sews,
Maud can bake a pie.
Chloë neither sews nor cooks,
Cannot swing a pen,
Doesn’t seem to run to books;
She just gets the men.

Winnie’s gayly dancing feet
Fly on fairy wings;
Silver bells ring, clear and sweet,
When Belinda sings.
Fair and true and talented
Are they all—but then
Little Chloë knocks them dead;
Chloë gets the men.